Henry Hazlitt Papers
Henry Hazlitt Papers
1920-1958
Hazlitt, Henry, 1894-1993.
6.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American journalist, editor, and author, specializing in economic subjects. Collection includes correspondence (1945-1958); book manuscripts, articles, editorials, reviews, speeches, and scrapbooks of clippings about Hazlitt.
149043
Biographical History
Henry Hazlitt (1894-1993) was an American libertarian economist and author. Hazlitt had a distinguished career as an economic journalist with the New York Times, the Wall Street Journal, and other leading metropolitan dailies, and at various times served as Economic Editor of Newsweek, literary editor for The Nation, and editor of American Mercury (replacing H.L. Mencken). He also authored several books on economic subjects.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Henry Hazlitt Papers consist of correspondence, miscellaneous, printed material, and writings.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. All other series are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
holds the papers of a number of important journalists; please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Hazlitt, Henry, 1894-1993.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Editors -- United States.; Journalism, Commercial.; Journalists -- United States.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Editorials.; Manuscripts for publication.; Reviews (documents); Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Authors.; Editors.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1945-1958 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Sketch of Hazlitt by George Stratton, 1948 (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Clippings about, scrapbooks; 2 volumes (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Anatomy of Criticism, typescript; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - The Foundations of Morality, notes, rough draft, typescript; 9 folders (Box 1)
    - Man vs. the Welfare State, notes, rough draft, 2 typescripts; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - A New American Constitution
      - Typescript, incomplete (Box 1)
      - Rough draft, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Untitled, on economic fallacies, rought draft; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Editorials and reviews
    - Jun 1934 - 22 Oct 1938, 3 volumes (Box 2)
    - 23 Oct 1938 - 15 May 1945, 3 volumes (Box 3)
  - Magazine articles
    - American Mercury, 6 issues (Box 3)
    - Atlantic, 1 issue (Box 3)
    - Current History, 4 issues (Box 3)
    - Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review, 2 issues (Box 3)
    - Modern Quarterly, 3 issues (Box 3)
    - Yale Review, 5 issues (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Rough drafts and notes (Box 4)
  - Magazines edited by
    - The Nation, 1930-1931 (Box 4)
    - The Nation, 1931-1933; 1939 (Box 5)
  - Speeches
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-1949 (Box 5)
  - News clippings
    - Miscellaneous, 8 folders (Box 5)